<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: speaking | Sasha Laundy]]></title>
  <link href="http://sursh.github.com/blog/categories/speaking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sursh.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-12T21:10:16-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://sursh.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sasha Laundy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Prep in the 24 Hours Before Giving a Conference Talk]]></title>
    <link href="http://sursh.github.com/blog/2015/02/23/how-i-prep-in-the-24-hours-before-a-conference-talk/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-23T16:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sursh.github.com/blog/2015/02/23/how-i-prep-in-the-24-hours-before-a-conference-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I gave a talk at Strata, O'Reilly's data science conference. Every time I give a talk I get a little bit better at it. I've seen a lot about how to propose talks and prepare slides, but less written about preparing right before your talk. Here's what I've figured out works best for me. I'd also really love to <a href="http://twitter.com/sashalaundy">hear from you</a> about how you prepare!</p>

<p>Part of my motivation for a behind-the-scenes post like this is that beginners compare polished final products to their own messy work. It is important to know that behind every polished talk there is no magic, just messy work! Lots and lots of messy work.</p>

<p>So here is my messy work. Here are some things I did this time that worked well.</p>

<p>First of all, <strong>I signed up to give the talk beforehand at a different conference</strong> in my hometown. This forced me to prepare <em>months</em> ahead of time and I was able to gather some helpful feedback. This is a GREAT idea and I plan to do it as much as possible.</p>

<p>By the time I was getting on the plane, I had 80% of the slides I needed already created. So in the 24 hours before the talk, here's how I prepared:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I paged through my old <strong>slides</strong> and decided what sections to cut out. I needed to cut the talk from 30 minutes to 16 minutes, and some pieces of it were 'nice to have' but not critical to my main points. I left placeholders where I thought I needed to add slides. It's really tempting at this point to fuss with the slides forever. Don't!</p></li>
<li><p>I immediately did a <strong>live runthrough</strong>! I just stood up and started talking over my slides as if I were presenting for real. This is so awkward at first but a few minutes in you'll be sailing! There were some rough spots but are never as many as I expect, which makes me feel really good! A large part of being prepared is managing your own emotions so this is actually really important!</p></li>
<li><p>I used Keynote to <strong>record</strong> this runthrough, which is very easy to do (I love Keynote). I then listened to it and noted rough spots: places where I rambled, tough transitions, and slides that need to be adjusted or removed.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/f.cl.ly/items/1Y05452c1Y3S471Y0m12/prep%201.JPG" title="Talk preparation" alt="A picture of my laptop and notes on a hotel dresser."></p>

<p><em>Preparing in my hotel room.</em></p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/f.cl.ly/items/2F0T3S201z3A2n2z0p2d/prep%202.JPG" title="Notes on what to change" alt="A picture of notes I took on my talk."></p>

<p><em>Notes on what to change for next time.</em></p>

<ul>
<li><p>At this point, I paid closest attention to the <strong>transitions</strong>. If I made a slide I probably know what goes on it, but what goes between it and the next one is sometimes rough at this stage. I like each slide to be set up by my words before it comes on, and transitions are absolutely key to the feeling of continuity. I sometimes leave extremely brief notes to myself in all caps in the presenter notes just in case I brainfart on stage.</p></li>
<li><p>When I did this rough runthrough, I did it standing up and with my clicker. I tried to <strong>picture the conference room</strong> in front of me. That way, it's not as surprising to walk up there on stage and I could be nice and calm during the real thing.</p></li>
<li><p>I made sure I knew how to get <strong>presenter tools</strong> to appear when I plug my computer into the big screen. Hint: you need to know the menu-bar-dragging trick in Display Preferences.</p></li>
<li><p>I wrote a little stickie that said 'TALK SLOWLY :)' and put it next to the keyboard on my laptop</p></li>
<li><p>I made PDF copies and put <strong>backups</strong> in Dropbox, just in case my dog ate my laptop on the way to the conference.</p></li>
<li><p>I made a <strong><a href="/talks/data-vitals">quick little landing page</a></strong> for the talk. I pointed to it from the most recent blog post and a pinned tweet so people could find and bookmark it during the talk. I added useful stuff to it right after the talk. The bulk of your audience may not even be in the room with you so this is a great way to get the most value out of your talk. For example, there were about 30 people listening to my PyData NYC talk, and at the time of this writing over 1,000 people have watched my video on Youtube.</p></li>
<li><p>And of course, I <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/amy_cuddy_your_body_language_shapes_who_you_are?language=en">power posed</a> :)</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This is what I've found to work for me for prepping in the 24 hours before the talk. What works for you?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Our Talk at Strata]]></title>
    <link href="http://sursh.github.com/blog/2014/10/21/our-talk-at-strata/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T10:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://sursh.github.com/blog/2014/10/21/our-talk-at-strata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I attended O'Reilly's data conference, Strata. I had a great time, including  co-presenting with my colleague <a href="http://shron.net">Max Shron</a> on the topic of <a href="http://strataconf.com/stratany2014/public/schedule/detail/36730">Solving the Right Problem</a>.</p>

<p>Based off the material in <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920029182.do">his book</a>, we argued that it is easy to crunch some numbers and feel like you're doing data science, but in the end to come up empty-handed since you didn't pick the right problem in the first place. This is a particular danger since data scientists love data and programming and the latest tools, so it can be very tempting to just dive into the data set without first considering where you'll end up.</p>

<p>We looked to the design world as a case study for how other disciplines have handled this very same problem, and propose that it's not enough to be technically and mathematically competent. Effective data scientists must also be skilled at drawing out the <em>actual need</em> from underneath the <em>stated need</em>.</p>

<p>The second half of the talk, where we lay out a framework for structuring scope conversations, was drawn from previous talks Max has given. This iteration of the talk saw two new things. First, I added more justification and urgency around why you should care about doing this well. I imagine that everyone who chose to be in our session already believes this, but chances are extremely good that there are <em>other people</em> in their organization that are skeptical. Hopefully our arguments are portable enough that attendees can persuade their coworkers and managers.</p>

<p>The second thing I added were symptoms of scoping poorly. Just as it's difficult to see that you're in the Matrix when you're in it, it's difficult to know that you're bad at scoping when you're bad at it. The presentation has four red flags so you can spot weak scoping and have the language to address it. The nice thing about these is that once you give them a name, everyone on your team is more likely to spot them and call them out.</p>

<p>O'Reilly is working on the video and we are working on the annotated slides. I'll update this post when they're out. In the meantime, please enjoy this totally unrelated visualization of the most popular American names over time:</p>

<iframe src="http://giphy.com/embed/5xtDarJpumZXFpm3tf2?html5=true" width="480" height="303" frameBorder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>I spent most of the rest of the conference on the "hallway track" meeting new folks and catching up with colleagues from around the world. The sessions look <em>awesome</em> and I bookmarked a bunch of them to watch later. Literally too many to list right now. Will pare them down the list for the next post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
