<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vim | Sasha Laundy]]></title>
  <link href="http://sursh.github.com/blog/categories/vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sursh.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-22T13:50:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://sursh.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sasha Laundy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm switching to vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://sursh.github.com/blog/2014/08/27/switching-to-vim/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-27T09:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://sursh.github.com/blog/2014/08/27/switching-to-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I should really have switched to vim ten years ago when I first started using the command line. But vim has a hell of a hill to get over, and I never made it high enough to keep going. I'm revisiting it because I love keyboard shortcuts! Once they're in your brain, you hardly have to think to move the whole program around at a blazing speed. Then you get to feel like a wizard.</p>

<p>Starting August 1, I deleted my symlink to <code>subl</code> and went cold turkey. It's slowed me down pretty significantly, but that's been a great incentive to set aside time every day to learn new vim stuff, and investing in the tools you use all day every day is always a great investment. I still feel pretty clumsy, but I now find myself editing non-code things in vim! Which is a good sign!</p>

<h2>Resources I'm Using</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>I've been working my way through <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Practical-Vim-Thought-Pragmatic-Programmers/dp/1934356980/">Practical Vim</a>, which is great at getting you <em>thinking</em> in the vim way. I suspect this will make me effective much faster than just googling for things as they come up.</p></li>
<li><p>When I want to look something up on the fly, Google usually points me to the <a href="http://vim.wikia.com/wiki/">Vim tips wiki</a>, which is <em>encyclopedic</em> for one-off solutions and quick fixes, even if they're not well contextualized.</p></li>
<li><p>I've been pestering my colleagues, developer friends, and other Hacker School folks for their favorite config and tips and tricks, which has been very fruitful.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>ALSO, I bought the domain thedailyvim.com, and am considering setting up a daily tips feed there. <a href="https://twitter.com/SashaLaundy">Send me a tweet</a> if that's something you'd be interested in!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
